<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Snoozetime's webpage (Posts about reading)</title><link>http://snoozetime.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://snoozetime.github.io/categories/reading.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2018 &lt;a href="mailto:benoit.eudier@gmail.com"&gt;Snoozetime&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 Nov 2018 08:57:36 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Fantasy novel series, and the Wait</title><link>http://snoozetime.github.io/posts/fantasy-novel-series-and-the-wait/</link><dc:creator>Snoozetime</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
I've always been an avid reader of long fantasy novel series. As a kid, I used
to read Lord of the ring, Harry Potter (does it count? Yes it does!) and
basically everything I could put my hand on.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
More recently I've been a huge fan of the work of Brandon Sanderson. For those
who don't know, Sandersonis the epic fantasy writer. He builds entire world
in different series of books that are somewhat connected in the
grander scheme: &lt;a href="https://brandonsanderson.com/"&gt;Sanderson website&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So yes, I really love epic Fantasy. But amazing book series come with a big
caveat: the Wait. As opposed to the Thrill while reading, the Wait is the
excruciable period from when I finish a book until the next one is released.
Let's take a few example: The Stormlight Archive by Sanderson is a novel
series which contains 3 books at the moment:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The Way of Kings, published August 31, 2010
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Words of Radiance, published March 4, 2014
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Oathbringer, published November 14, 2017
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I've been in a state of passive suffering for at least 7 years.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Another great series of novel is &lt;i&gt;The Kingkiller Chronicle&lt;/i&gt; by Patrick
Rothfuss. Here, the last book has been published 7 years ago!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
And also, Game of Thrones people?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
To be clear, I am very grateful to the authors out there that are
publishing these fantastic books. But how to satisfy the Wait? I've found
two ways some far:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="org-ol"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read more novels. This has the benefit of making me forget a bit about
the previous book I read, but it might add more series to the wait list.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Read novel series that have already ended. That way no more wait. Just a
feeling of emptiness at the end.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description><category>fantasy</category><category>reading</category><guid>http://snoozetime.github.io/posts/fantasy-novel-series-and-the-wait/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 26 Apr 2018 05:25:14 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>